et397 [at] cornell.edu https://emtseng.me

Emily Tseng

Research Interests

I study how technology facilitates harms for vulnerable populations, with a focus on enabling safe and consentful research with these groups. My research builds on techniques in *human-computer interaction* and *computer security and privacy* to design, build, and deploy novel sociotechnical systems in real-world contexts, with the goal of improving digital security and privacy for vulnerable and marginalized people.

Education

2019-now **Ph.D. at Cornell University,** Department of Information Science Advised by Nicola Dell and Deborah Estrin.

2017-19 **M.S. at Cornell Tech,** Information Science - Health Tech

Relevant coursework: Applied Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language

Processing, Human-Computer Interaction, Interactive Device Design.

Advised by Nicola Dell and Deborah Estrin.

2010-14 **B.A. at Princeton University,** Ecology & Evolutionary Biology

GPA: 3.5/4.0

GPA: 3.9/4.0

Concentration in Global Health and Health Policy. Studied epidemiology, journalism and social policy with a focus on predictive modeling of infectious disease epidemics. Advised by Bryan Grenfell and Tiffany Bogich.

Awards & Honors

| 2021 | Digital Life Initiative Doctoral Fellowship |
|------|---|
| 2020 | Best Paper Award, ACM CSCW |
| 2020 | Distinguished Paper Award, USENIX Security Symposium |
| 2020 | Internet Defense Prize (third place), USENIX Security Symposium |
| 2020 | CRA-WP Grad Cohort for Women (postponed due to COVID-19, attended in 2021) |
| 2019 | Best Paper Honorable Mention, ACM CSCW |
| 2019 | Advocate of New York City Award, Mayor's Office to End Domestic & Gender-Based Violence |
| 2019 | Cornell University Information Science Department Fellowship |
| | First-year fellowship awarded for exceptional preparation & promise (top 1.5% of applicants). |
| 2017 | Cornell Tech merit scholarship for Master's-level study |
| 2014 | Top Senior Thesis in Mathematical Modeling, Princeton University Department of Ecology |
| | & Evolutionary Biology |
| 2014 | Society of Sigma Xi (scientific research honor society), Princeton University |

Refereed Conference and Journal Publications

- 1. **Tseng, E.**, Freed, D., Engel, K., Ristenpart, T., and Dell, N. 2021. *A Digital Safety Dilemma: Analysis of Computer-Mediated Computer Security Interventions for Intimate Partner Violence During COVID-19.* In Proceedings of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '21). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA. pdf. online.video.
- 2. Bellini, R., **Tseng, E.,** McDonald, N., Greenstadt, R., McCoy, D., Ristenpart, T. and Dell, N. "So-called privacy breeds evil": Narrative Justifications for Intimate Partner Surveillance in Online Forums. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Issue CSCW. 2020. pdf. Best Paper Award.
- 3. **Tseng, E.,** Bellini, R., McDonald, N., Danos, M., Greenstadt, R., McCoy, D., Dell, N. and Ristenpart, T. 2020. The Tools and Tactics Used in Intimate Partner Surveillance: An Analysis of Online Infidelity Forums. 29th USENIX Security Symposium. pdf. online.

 Distinguished Paper Award.

 Internet Defense Prize, third prize.
- 4. Sterling, MR, **Tseng**, E, Poon, A, Cho, J, Avgar, AC, Kern, LM, Ankuda, CK, Dell, N. 2020. Experiences of Home Health Care Workers in New York City During the Coronavirus Disease 2019 Pandemic: A Qualitative Analysis. JAMA Internal Medicine. pdf. online.
- 5. **Tseng, E.,** Okeke, F., Sterling, M., and Dell, N. 2020. "We can learn. Why not?": Designing Technologies to Engender Equity for Home Health Aides. In Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA. pdf. online.
- 6. Sterling, M. R., Dell, N., Piantella, B., Cho, J., Kaur, H., **Tseng, E.,** Okeke, F., Brown, M., Leung, P. B. K., Silva, A. F., Shaw, A. L., Kern, L. M. 2020. *Understanding the Workflow of Home Healthcare for Patients with Heart Failure: Challenges and Opportunities*. Journal of General Internal Medicine. pdf. online.
- 7. Freed, D.*, Havron, S.*, **Tseng, E.**, Gallardo A., Chatterjee, R., Ristenpart, T., and Dell, N.. 2019. "Is my phone hacked?" Analyzing Clinical Computer Security Interventions with Survivors of Intimate Partner Violence. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction: Vol. 3, Issue CSCW, Article 202. <u>pdf</u>. <u>online</u>.
 - Best Paper Honorable Mention.
- 8. Okeke, F., **Tseng, E.,** Piantella, B., Brown, M., Kaur, H., Sterling, M., and Dell, N. 2019. *Technology, Home Health Care, and Heart Failure: A Qualitative Analysis with Multiple Stakeholders.* ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing & Sustainable Societies (COMPASS 2019). pdf. online.

Teaching and Advising

Cornell University, remote due to COVID-19

| Teaching Assistant, Summer School on Designing Technology for Social Impact | Summer 2021 |
|---|-------------|
| Teaching Assistant, CS 1340 / INFO 1260: Choices and Consequences in Computing, | Spring 2021 |
| Professors Jon Kleinberg and Karen Levy | |

Teaching Assistant, CS 5682 / INFO 6410: HCI & Design, Professor Nicola Dell Fall 2020

Cornell Tech, New York, NY

| Teaching Assistant, INFO 6940: Technology & Social Justice, Professor Nicola Dell | Spring 2020 |
|---|-------------|
| Research Internship Supervisor, Technion + Cornell Tech Intern Program | Fall 2019 |
| Grader, CS 5740: Natural Language Processing, Professor Yoav Artzi | Spring 2019 |
| Lead Teaching Assistant, Product Studio, Professor Deborah Estrin | Fall 2018 |

Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, NY

Guest Lecturer, HCPL 8101: Digital Health, Professor Deborah Estrin Summer 2020

Fullstack Academy, New York, NY

Software Engineering Teaching Fellow

Summer 2017

- Taught and mentored 80+ students at a selective software engineering bootcamp.
- Delivered 10-minute talk on inclusive design and web accessibility: https://youtu.be/NQP8yg81KZ8

Presentations

Invited Talks

2021, MIT Visualization Group

2020, United Hospital Fund/Greater New York Hospital Association Annual Symposium

2020, MIT CSAIL Security Seminar

2020, Facebook Research

2020, Precision Behavioral Health Initiative, Cornell Tech

2020, Weill Cornell Medical College

Conference Talks

2021, A Digital Safety Dilemma, ACM CHI [video]

2020, The Tools and Tactics of Intimate Partner Violence, USENIX Security Symposium [video]

2020, Designing for Equity for Home Health Aides, ACM CHI (canceled due to COVID-19)

Academic and University Service

2021, Diversity, Equity and Inclusion Strategic Committee at Cornell Tech, PhD Representative

2021, CHI, Student Volunteer (fully remote conference)

2021, Faculty Hiring Committee at Cornell Tech, PhD Representative

2020, PhDs at Cornell Tech, Co-President

2019, Health Tech. NYC speaker series, Organizer

Reviewer

ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)

ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)

USENIX Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS)

Current Research

Understanding working alliance in online psychotherapy

PIs: Tanzeem Choudhury, Ph.D., Cristian Danescu-Niculescu-Mizil, Ph.D., Deborah Estrin, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Investigating the use of generative modeling techniques to understand how working alliance manifests, develops, and dissipates on a widely used platform for text-based psychotherapy.

Understanding online abuser communities in intimate partner surveillance (IPS) *PIs: Nicola Dell, Ph.D. and Thomas Ristenpart, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)*

- Built a web scraping pipeline collecting data from public forums where abusers discuss IPS tactics.
- Analyzed how these forums manifest specific tactics and narrative justifications for abuse [2,3].

Clinical computer security for victims and survivors of IPV

PIs: Nicola Dell, Ph.D. and Thomas Ristenpart, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Conducting a field study of a "tech clinic" intervention for victims of IPV in New York City, in partnership with the Mayor's Office to End Domestic and Gender-Based Violence. [1,7]

Community-engaged technology design to support home health aides caring for adults with heart failure PIs: Nicola Dell, Ph.D. (Cornell Tedh), Madeline Sterling, M.D. M.P.H. (Weill Cornell Medicine)

- Performed qualitative analysis of interviews with 50+ aides, nurses, physicians, social workers and agency leaders to understand the technology ecosystem around the home care of heart failure [6,8].
- Synthesized results into a functional prototype used in a participatory design study with aides, nurses, and other stakeholders to elicit how aides might use technology to achieve equity goals [5].
- Interviewed 20+ aides working in New York City during pandemic lockdowns in spring 2020 to understand how COVID-19 has affected their experiences [4].

Past Research

Extracting family history from unstructured clinical notes

- Developed a statistical model (LSTM-CRF) extracting family history information from unstructured text in patient information questionnaires.
- Awarded student travel grant to present at the OHNLP/BioCreativ workshop at ACM-BCB 2018.

Evaluating the usability of a personal data filtering interface

PI: Deborah Estrin, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Conducted a Mechanical Turk experiment evaluating the usability of an interface for filtering sensitive data from a user's Google Takeout export.

Prototyping a tool for real-time smartphone-based mood tracking *PI: JP Pollak, Ph.D. (Cornell Tedn)*

- Prototyped and tested an intentive computing tool for logging emotional states in real time.
- Examine its usability and utility in managing anxiety through interviews and observational studies.

Modeling the dynamics of enterovirus-71 in Taiwan: An application of the TSIR model *PI: Bryan Grenfell, Ph.D. (Princeton University)*

- Developed a time-series model of the impact of vaccination on EV-71 infection rates in Taiwan.
- Awarded departmental prize for excellence in mathematical modeling [poster].

Relevant Industry Experience

Pfizer, Inc., New York, NY

Summer Associate Summer 2018

- Led a team of UX researchers and technologists to synthesize user stories, product requirements and storyboards for a care navigation product addressing health disparities within the Welsh NHS.
- Interviewed domain experts on the feasibility of a consumer voice product for patient support.

Biomeme, Inc., Philadelphia, PA

Product & Business Development Associate

2014 - 2016

- Developed an at-home sexual health diagnostic for a national reproductive healthcare provider.
- Developed a point-of-care influenza diagnostic with a federal disease control agency, resulting in a pilot program in a clinic network in Nairobi, Kenya.
- Conducted UX studies to guide development of a consumer-facing tool for personal DNA analysis.

Oxford University Clinical Research Unit (OUCRU), Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam

Research Intern Summer 2013

- Conducted literature reviews, performed data analyses (R) and mapped patient enrollment (GIS, Illustrator) for ongoing clinical studies at a tertiary tuberculosis hospital.
- Funded by the Center for Health & Wellbeing at Princeton University, through the Gates Foundation's Global Health Grand Challenge.

Doctors Without Borders / Medecins Sans Frontieres (MSF), New York, NY

Editorial & Multimedia Intern

Summer 2011, 2012

- Produced audio, video & web features on MSF field staff at humanitarian aid sites worldwide.

The Daily Princetonian, Princeton, NJ

Managing Editor

2013 - 2014

- Led 100+ staff of a collegiate news organization publishing in print 5x/week and online 24/7.
- Built web and data journalism departments, and expanded the paper's multimedia capabilities.

Skills

- **Human-Centered Design** | Interviewing, contextual enquiry, survey design, thematic analysis, prototyping (Sketch, Photoshop, Illustrator, InDesign, InVision)
- **Data Science** | Quantitative analysis and statistical modeling (Python, R, MATLAB), modern machine learning (scikit-learn, Dynet, Tensorflow, Pytorch)
- **Software Development** | Full-stack software engineering (JavaScript, Node.JS, React, HTML, CSS/Sass), Agile development, cloud deployment tools (AWS, Heroku), Git
- Communication | Writing, editing, public speaking, multimedia production (audio and video)